How's your day going so far?
>> Good.
>> Great.
Um
So, I've got about 25 minutes or
something.
Um and I'm going to try and talk about
building AI-native companies. This is
based on a talk I gave about a month,
maybe 6 weeks ago. It's on YouTube. Um
I've updated it. I've added some
thoughts. I think the main caveat I want
to start with is
no one knows how to do this.
And so, this is um
very theoretical.
It's based on uh hundreds of YC
companies that we're working with right
now. Um lots and lots of people are
trying things. And I think if anyone
tells you they've got it all figured
out, they are probably lying. I think
internally at YC, we have an amazing
software team. We've been pushing the
boundaries of
I think what LLMs can do for a couple of
years now.
I think we have a bunch of really
interesting use cases.
Um which I'll I'll give examples of
those as we go through. But, I I don't
think we've got it
I don't think we've yet got it fully
figured out, but I expect
um
by the end of 2026 or possibly by the
first batch in 2027,
we
it will be possible, I don't know if
we'll take the PR risk of it, it will be
possible to
from end to end have an AI fully read
all the applications,
pick the companies to interview, conduct
the interview, select the companies to
fund, give them advice throughout the
batch on how to do like run their
companies more effectively,
introduce them to investors, review
their pitch decks, and then debug their
pitch meetings.
I think an AI will be able to do all of
that end to end.
Probably by the end of this year, if not
by the first 3 months of next year.
We've got quite a lot of it working
already. We're exposing a lot to our
founders. I'll tell you more about that,
but that's sort of where this talk has
come from. So, what is an AI native
company? Well,
the first thing to start with is what is
not an AI native company.
This is how
the Roman legions were were structured.
The smallest unit was the
contubernium. So, eight soldiers who
share a tent, equipment, and a mule, and
there's a decanus, and then 10 of these
things called a
contubernia form a century, which is
actually 80 men, not 100, which is very
confusing. But, you see this kind of
hierarchical um
way of organizing humans, right? The
Roman legions used this to project power
across North Africa, across
um
Near Asia, up into the UK, up to
Hadrian's Wall. This was the way that
the Roman Empire projected power.
And they would pass information down and
receive reports up. And a human being
was responsible for being that conduit
the whole way.
And bizarrely,
like 2,000 years later,
we're still basically running the same
kind of thing. And then like they look
slightly different. This is a Carpathia
tweet, uh which I thought was very good.
But, um
like they're all organized slightly
differently, but the same principle is
true, which is that humans are the
conduit for information going up and
down
um
up and down the rungs, right? And so,
there's a Jack Dorsey tweet tweet which
kicked this whole thing off about 2
months ago. There's an underlying
assumption that organizations have to be
hierarchically
organized with humans as a coordinating
mechanism.
And I think
basically AI breaks that apart. So, you
don't have to have
humans as a coordinating mechanism
any longer. And I basically think most
companies have mis-
Misunderstood is the wrong word. Most
companies sort of experienced ChatGPT as
a Q&A bot. They put put ans- They put
questions in, they get answers out. And
then maybe they've sort of moved to
longer running
perhaps what you might call an agentic
system or something. But basically, you
tell you ask the agent to go and do
something, it goes away until it gets
stuck,
and it comes back to you, and you as a
human are like the gating mechanism. And
so, while you are asleep,
the the thing can't work, right? Like if
it stops halfway through at 3:00 in the
morning, like it's waiting on input from
you, it can't go anymore. You as a human
are the gating mechanism.
And so, you you know, you can do things
like making engineers 20% more
productive, you can add co-pilots for
lawyers to make their existing workflows
get a little better, you can ship more
software with AI, but really all of
these things um
the men in the suits are coming for me.
I don't know what to
I don't know.
um
uh really
it's dependent on humans being the
coordinating mechanism in all of these
places. And if you think about it not
just as like increasing productivity,
but in terms of new capabilities,
Huh, that's interesting. Oh, there we
go. um
W- We're basically
a single person can do way more work
than previously thousands of people.
Your entire company becomes queryable,
and you're not just shipping more
software, but the the software you ship
is like agent native. I These are a lot
of buzzwords. I'm going to go into more
detail about what I mean.
AI At the moment, AI A lot of companies
like bolting AI on onto the side of the
company, right? In all the ways we've
spoken about. The Q- question answer
bots, they're sort of very um
lightweight agents that can call tools
effectively like a web search or
something like that.
um
But if you
think about the company
as a series of self-improving AI loops
from the ground up, you actually get to
a very very different conclusion. Okay?
Previously, AI is like make each person
20% more productive or 30% more
productive.
What happens if we reimagine the company
as a series of AI loops? What is an AI
loop?
It's
basically like um
So, the top you've got
um product telemetry inbound messages.
This is like data from the real world,
right? Like billing signals, support
tickets, code changes, stuff that gives
you information in.
And then you go down to the perhaps a
policy layer, which is like what rules
can it um what rules constrain the AI?
What things it must ask approval for?
What does it have to log?
Um you have a tool layer where it can
call perhaps internal AI APIs, um send
emails, uh update the billing, um and
you might have APIs for this or MCP or
whatever. And then you have a series of
quality gates, which it which could be a
human, and I'd argue probably should not
be a human in in all but the most
extreme cases, but the quality gate can
often be a second adversarial LLM. It
might be something that's that's looking
at the output saying, are we suffering
from prompt injection here? Or
in a case of a bank, are we giving
financial advice here, yes or no? And if
we are, we can't, you know, like
constrain it or
a really easy example for engineers is
like
um the quality gate might simply be a
second model doing code review.
Um
and then a learning mechanism, which is
basically you loop back around, right?
You deploy the thing, you make the
change, and you see how it impacts the
real world.
If you can do this entire loop without a
human,
your product starts improving itself
when you're sleeping. Can you scroll
down a little bit to the bottom of this,
please?
Yeah, all the way to the bottom. Thank
you very much. So, um
the first time I saw these things, it
like broke my brain a little bit. Um
internally at YC, uh we've got a lot
we've got a data on 7,000 companies,
20,000 founders, like many hundreds of
thousands of applications.
So, a year or two ago, we built an AI
agent that it basically human it's like
English to SQL, right? Like it's a
simple data querying agent. You can be
like,
what was a split of European versus uh
American founders this batch?" And it
would go and translate that human query
into SQL and run it and come back with
the answer. It's like, yeah, pretty
pretty magical.
But that feels like a tool that kind of
makes a data analyst 20% or 30% more
productive. For me, actually makes me as
a partner
10% or 20% more productive and I don't
have to hire a data analyst.
It was fine.
And it would keep hitting edge cases or
like not be able to do certain things.
I'd be like, "Oh, that's annoying."
And then we shipped something about two
or three months ago, which for me was
like the head explosion moment, which
was a second agent, which uh sort of
lives on top of this um data query
agent. And the second agent runs
overnight and it looks for all the
queries that any human has done during
the day
and it looks for
success and failure.
So, the success is like, yeah, I copy
it, I send the email, I do whatever. The
failure is like, ah this isn't
work or it I hit a permission issue or
whatever. Like, the database index
doesn't work or it has
it requests some permission it doesn't
have. And then that second AI agent
overnight goes and puts in pull requests
to fix all of the problems from the day
before.
And so, if you go back as a human on the
second day and run the same query as
yesterday, it now works.
And so, this process of like evaluating
what the system is doing and then
proposing changes to the system and
updating the system makes the whole
thing self-improving.
And that for me was like a
head explosion moment. I think if you
were here earlier for um James's talk
from PostHog, they basically have the
same thing for products now. They take
in all your product telemetry and they
see where it's breaking and then they
put in pull requests and eventually auto
merge those pull requests. So, your
entire product surface will become
self-improving. It will just dynamically
You'll have a a bunch of headline
metrics you want to optimize for. You'll
have a bunch of
product like vision documents, which
says, "This is the kind of thing we want
to build. Hit This is in scope and out
of scope. And the AI will basically look
at your product telemetry, come up with
ideas, deploy those ideas, test them
with humans, and see if it moved the
needle or not, and just self-improve.
Copacetic um
uh
had a great tweet about 3 weeks ago now
on like the auto research thing.
Basically applying this to machine
learning. Just having the AI I think it
was on GPT-2 equivalent or something
like that. But coming up with research
ideas, testing it, running overnight,
and just hill climbing. All this is just
hill climbing. If you have a an end
measurable outcome,
you can just come up with ideas, you can
test it. Did we go up the hill or down
the hill? If down hill, discard. If up,
like keep. And just keep hill climbing.
And
computer systems are really really good
at this kind of hill climbing work
because they never stop.
They will just run indefinitely
indefinitely until you reach local
maximum.
It's kind of cool cuz you they don't
have to sleep.
Um
Another example from YC, we started
recording office hours about 6 months
ago.
Um
and I was given the job of rewriting a
section of We have a user manual
internally.
Um which is written over the last 15
years. And it's like
500 pages long. And a lot of it was very
very good like 5 years ago. And then AI
happened. And like honestly a bunch of
the advice is just not relevant anymore.
And I had the job of rewriting a bunch
of this stuff. And I like procrastinated
and procrastinated and procrastinated.
And we started recording the office
hours 6 months ago. Now we have like I
don't know 3 or 4,000 hours of office
hours recorded. And someone on the team,
Harj I think it was, had the idea of
like what if we just transcribe and then
mine all of the advice we actually give
in office hours, and then use that to
rewrite the user manual.
And so
>> [snorts]
>> when the advice changes, the AI will see
what the humans are saying, extract the
insight, and just rewrite the user
manual, and push it.
So it becomes this like living guide of
how we actually advise in companies.
And then obviously once you've got it in
a user manual, you just make the entire
thing queryable to an advice agent,
right? Like if a if a founder asks us a
question in Slack and we get a lot of
questions that are pretty similar,
honestly, like how should I price my
first customer or my third customer is
is about to churn, what should I do or
this customer has asked for this
esoteric feature, what I'm just like
we've answered versions of this question
like 500 times.
And so now
the AI can give not just Tom's answer,
but like here's how
Niccolo would answer it or here's how
Harj would answer it. I think you can
actually get superhuman advice from this
thing because it's able to
recall perfectly and access the
intelligence of 16 partners, not just
one with fallible memory.
And so you can kind of see how this
these like loops
can run in the background and get better
and better and better and better.
And then I think
you
give them a virtual machine.
So, you give your agent a virtual
machine
with things like
tools, so search the web, crawl your
internal company directory, search your
Slack history,
persistent file storage, so it can write
it can come up with a plan and write the
plan to disk so if it fails halfway
through it can resume.
And then it if it needs to, it can write
code and execute the code to solve a
problem.
And then see how that worked against the
plan and adjust and repeat.
And now you've basically got an AI
employee.
And I
we're at the very, very early stage of
this with something like Open Claw or
Hermes is a basically VMs with an agent
living inside on a on basically on a
repeating loop.
>> [gasps]
>> So, where we are now, right? I think YC
has a few of these loops internally. I
think the next thing that happens
like it occasionally a human has to
intervene, right? We're like, "Well, the
loop's going wrong." Whatever. Like,
"Let's take some insight from there put
it over there." I think the thing that
happens afterwards is the loops start
talking to each other or the AI
employees start communicating with each
other
to share ideas and re-plan and assess
and and whatever. And you end up with
this like
I mean, company brain is is like
an overused term. Now, it got very very
popular about 6 weeks ago and as of like
2 weeks ago it's I see people in the
audience with company brain written on a
t-shirt now.
There he is.
>> [laughter]
>> Um
but what So, what is this as an idea?
It's the
Mhm.
I'm going to steal some of Jack Dorsey's
words, but in a conventional company
intelligence is spread throughout the
people
and the hierarchy
roots it.
So,
in this new model
intelligence lives in the system.
What I mean by that basically is that
um
lots and lots of companies try and write
down standard operating procedures,
right? Like, the way things should be
done. But then when you actually observe
people, how they actually do the job
they're like, "Oh, well, in in this edge
case it's really I should do this other
thing." And there's a lot of stuff in
people's heads
that if it weren't in people's heads and
it was actually written down
you'd get a lot of value out of it. And
so, this [snorts] idea of a company
brain I think is the combination of like
basically taking all of the
data in your company and that's things
like YC's application data, it's it's
transcripts of every call with with
every meeting with every founder, it's
the advice we give
um the way we pick companies. And then
you
record that and make it legible. You
make You make it so that the AI can
access all of it.
And then you have a bunch of these
reinforcing loops that run
indefinitely and then are able to talk
to each other, and the entire thing
becomes a self-improving company.
I think that's basically where we're
going.
That you just pump tokens in, you get
access to all of your data, and the
entire thing becomes self-improving.
>> [snorts]
>> And
people live at the edge.
Right? So, you have this kind of company
brain, this data, these self-reinforcing
loops, and then the human beings live
around the edge where this intelligence
makes contact with reality.
So, I think Jack Dorsey said, "People
reach into places the model can't yet
go.
They sense things the model can't
perceive. Intuition,
opinionated direction, cultural context,
trust dynamic, the feeling in a room."
Um they make the calls the model
shouldn't make on its own, especially
ethical decisions, novel situations, and
high-stakes moment where the cost of
being wrong is existential.
A world model, this company brain that
can't touch the real world, is just a
database.
And so, these humans, what what he's
saying, I think, is the humans uh
in the sales calls, right? They're like
visiting the client office to reassure
people, to convince the CEO, to pitch
the investor. It's all of the
emotional uh kind of interpersonal stuff
that the humans are there for.
But, the humans are no longer necessary
to do the information routing. Right?
Like, all of the information is routed
automatically to the person who needs
it. They don't need to go through layers
and layers of management to get
approved.
Um
And so,
that's basically what I think companies
are going to be. They're going to be
much, much smaller. They're going to be
centered around a kind of company brain,
and the people will interface with the
real world, and then feed all that
information back into into the brain.
A reasonable question is,
"Sounds great in theory. How do like
this seems like sci-fi kind of. Like,
will it happen? Who knows. What can we
actually do now to make it happen?"
Um and so, practically, these are the
tips we're giving founders right now.
The first is I'd burn tokens, not
headcount.
So, we're seeing founders get to
demo day with a million dollars of
revenue, and some getting to series A
um with 10 million of revenue with like
a fraction of the the people they had
before.
You can argue about whether it's a
thousand X or whatever, but it's
multiple times more, right? Like someone
a polyglot who really knows how to use
these tools is worth many, many times uh
the people before.
Um
and you can just do this As a result,
the headcount of the whole company is
going to be less.
In particular, it means no middle
management. We just don't think you need
layers and layers of like directors and
VPs anymore.
The key roles for me are the like the
IC. Everyone has to be a individual
contributor actually doing the work,
coming to meetings with working
prototypes, not decks.
And DRI like DRIs is for me actually the
biggest thing a lot of companies are
missing, which is like a single person
whose head is on the block to make
something happen. As soon as you have a
committee, I worked at a bank and we had
so many committees for everything,
and it grinds things to a halt. So,
having a single person who's directly
responsible for the outcome,
I think these are the most two important
the two most important roles.
And I think middle management is gone.
Practically speaking,
um I would try to make This is, by the
way, easier when you're starting out. I
would make everything in your
organization legible to Legible's like a
really popular word in Silicon Valley
right now. It means you can read it.
Make all your data readable to AI.
That means recording everything,
transcribing literally every meeting.
Um
if you can't get access to Slack DMs, I
would ban the Slack DMs. Make everything
um in public channels the AI can access.
Every action needs to create an
artifact. It needs to create a uh
written or recorded version, otherwise
it basically didn't happen to the AI.
Ob- obviously, I think on-demand
internal software for all internal in uh
all company operations is
um
absolutely necessary.
A really cool thing we've just started
doing,
which I don't think we've spoken about
yet, um,
is, uh, and it's inevitable it comes out
anyway, so,
um,
obviously you record all your, um, sales
meetings, right?
And you can feed those sales meetings
back into an AI to be like, how did I do
with my sales meeting?
What if you also recorded all your
meetings with investors?
And you took those investor calls and
you had access to several hundred or
thousand companies that are all meeting
all the same investors every 3 months.
And the first thing you can do is tell
founders, here's what's going wrong with
your pitch. You spent 90% of the time
talking or you really fumbled this
question or you need to be much more
concise on your go-to-market. Very, very
easy to do and many of our founders are
taking 40 or 50 or 60 investor calls.
You just pump them in and the AI will,
if you're recording them, tell you
what's going well and what's going
badly.
But we also get data on the other side
of that conversation. These founders are
meeting the same investors. So, investor
X will definitely, here's how like, we
could simulate the investment call,
right? We could say, here's exactly how
Andreessen Horowitz does every single
investment call. Whereas, Founders Fund
will ask you this question, this
question or this particular partner will
always say, what's your wedge or what is
like, what's your motive Anthropic comes
after this?
And here's a great way to answer that.
And I'm sure I'm I don't feel bad about
doing this at all because I absolutely
know that those investors are also
recording this and pumping into their
AI.
>> [snorts]
>> And so, anyway, basically, if you can
record it, if you can make it legible,
then the AI can start to comprehend it
and give you superpowers. I will finish
on this. If you are starting a company
today,
would you build it like this?
And for, this was a talk to very early
stage YC founders. Most of you are even
earlier stage
and you're small enough to just build it
right from the start.
So, anyway, I'll finish there. I think
we have, oh, no, we'll just do questions
with all of us, I think, rather than me
taking questions on my own. Why did we
do that?
Thank you.
>> [applause]
>> Thank you.